window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Algorithms - Algorithms — Slot 17 (20 Questions)",
  "duration": 55,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Algorithms — Slot 17",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Give the correct matching for the following pairs: <br>\\(\\begin{array}{ll|ll}\\hline \\text{(A)} &amp; \\text{$O (\\log n)$} &amp; \\text{(P)} &amp; \\text{Selection sort} \\\\\\hline \\text{(B)} &amp; \\text{$O (n)$} &amp; \\text{(Q)}&amp; \\text{Insertion sort} \\\\\\hline \\text{(C)}&amp; \\text{$O (n \\log n)$} &amp; \\text{(R)} &amp; \\text{Binary search} \\\\\\hline \\text{(D)} &amp; \\text{$O (n^2)$} &amp;\\text{(S)} &amp; \\text{Merge sort} \\\\\\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A-R  B-P  C-Q  D-S</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A-R  B-P  C-S  D-Q</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A-P  B-R  C-S  D-Q</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A-P  B-S  C-R  D-Q</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A-R  B-P  C-S  D-Q</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1659/gate1998-1-22\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following algorithm design techniques is used in finding all pairs of shortest distances in a graph? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1998)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Greedy</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Divide and Conquer</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1658/gate1998-1-21-isro2008-16\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Let T(n) be the function defined by<br> \\(T(1) =1, \\: T(n) = 2T (\\lfloor \\frac{n}{2} \\rfloor ) + \\sqrt{n} \\text{ for } n \\geq 2\\).<br>Which of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = O \\sqrt{n}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=O(n)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = O (\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=O(n)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2247/gate1997-4-6\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>The correct matching for the following pairs is <br>\\(\\begin{array}{ll|ll}\\hline \\text{A.} &amp; \\text{All pairs shortest path} &amp; \\text{1.} &amp; \\text{Greedy} \\\\\\hline \\text{B.} &amp; \\text{Quick Sort} &amp; \\text{2.}&amp; \\text{Depth-First Search} \\\\\\hline \\text{C.}&amp; \\text{Minimum weight spanning tree} &amp; \\text{3.} &amp; \\text{Dynamic Programming} \\\\\\hline \\text{D.} &amp; \\text{Connected Components} &amp;\\text{4.} &amp; \\text{Divide and Conquer} \\\\\\hline \\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1997)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A-2 B-4 C-1 D-3</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>A-3 B-4 C-1 D-2</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>A-3 B-4 C-2 D-1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>A-4 B-1 C-2 D-3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>A-3 B-4 C-1 D-2</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2221/gate1997-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Quick-sort is run on two inputs shown below to sort in ascending order taking first element as pivot <br>\n(i).  \\(1, 2, 3, \\dots n\\)<br>\n(ii). \\(n, n-1, n-2, \\dots, 2, 1\\)<br>\nLet \\(C_1\\) and \\(C_2\\) be the number of comparisons made for the inputs (i) and (ii) respectively. Then, <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(C_1 \\lt C_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(C_1 = C_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(C_1 \\gt C_2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>we cannot say anything for arbitrary n</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(C_1 = C_2\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2744/gate1996-2-15\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The recurrence relation <br>\n\\(T(1) = 2\\)<br>\n\\(T(n) = 3T (\\frac{n}{4}) +n\\)<br>\nhas the solution \\(T(n)\\) equal to <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O (\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O\\left(n^\\frac{3}{4}\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2741/gate1996-2-12\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following is false? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1996)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(100n \\log n=O(\\frac{n\\log n}{100})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\sqrt{\\log n} = O(\\log\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\text{If  } \\; 0 \\lt x \\lt y \\text{ then } n^x = O\\left(n^y\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^n \\neq O\\left(nk\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\sqrt{\\log n} = O(\\log\\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2715/gate1996-1-11\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Merge sort uses: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1995)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Divide and conquer strategy</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking approach</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Heuristic search</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Greedy approach</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Divide and conquer strategy</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2592/gate1995-1-5\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following two functions: <br>\\(g_1(n) = \\begin{cases} n^3 \\text{ for } 0 \\leq n \\leq 10,000 \\\\ n^2 \\text{ for } n \\geq 10,000 \\end{cases}\\)<br>\\(g_2(n) = \\begin{cases} n \\text{ for } 0 \\leq n \\leq 100 \\\\ n^3 \\text{ for } n &gt; 100 \\end{cases}\\)<br>Which of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(g_1(n) \\text{ is } O(g_2(n))\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(g_1(n) \\text{ is } O(n^3)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(g_2(n) \\text{ is } O(g_1(n))\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(g_2(n) \\text{ is } O(n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(g_1(n) \\text{ is } O(g_2(n))\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2466/gate1994-1-23\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Algorithm design technique used in quicksort algorithm is? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Dynamic programming</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Backtracking</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Greedy method</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Divide and conquer</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2462/gate1994-1-19-isro2016-31\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>The recurrence relation that arises in relation with the complexity of binary search is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1994)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = 2T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+k, \\text{ k is a constant }\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+k, \\text{ k is a constant }\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+\\log n\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+k, \\text{ k is a constant }\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2444/gate1994-1-7-isro2017-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>\\( \\sum_{1\\leq k\\leq n} O(n)\\),  where \\(O(n)\\) stands for order \\(n\\) is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1993)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(n^3)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(3n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>E.</b> <p>\\(O(1.5n^2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n^2)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2305/gate1993-8-7\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Consider the undirected unweighted graph G. Let a breadth-first traversal of\nG be done starting from a node r . Let d(r,u) and d(r,v) be the lengths of the\nshortest paths form r to u and v respectively in G. If u is visited before v during\nthe breadth-first traversal, which of the following statements is correct ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>d(r,u) \\(\\lt\\) d(r,v)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>d(r,u) \\(\\leq\\) d(r,v)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>d(r,u) \\(\\gt\\)d(r,v)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>None of the above</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>d(r,u) \\(\\leq\\) d(r,v)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/732/gate2001-2-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Let  \\(f (n) =n^{2} logn\\)  and \\(g(n) = n(logn)^{10}\\) be two positive functions of n. Which of the following statements is correct ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>f (n) = O(g(n))and g(n) \\(\\neq\\) O(f (n))</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>g(n) = O(f (n)) and f (n) \\(\\neq\\) O(g(n))</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>f (n) \\(\\neq\\) O(g(n)) and g(n) \\(\\neq\\) O(f (n))</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>f (n) = O(g(n))and g(n) = O(f (n))</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>g(n) = O(f (n)) and f (n) \\(\\neq\\) O(g(n))</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/709/gate2001-1-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Randomized quicksort is an extension of quicksort where the pivot is chosen\nrandomly. What is the worst case complexity of sorting n numbers using\nrandomized quicksort ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2001)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O(nlogn)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(\\(n^{2}\\)\n)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O(n!)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>O(\\(n^{2}\\)\n)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/707/gate2001-1-14#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 16,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only: <br>\nWhich of the following problems is not NP-hard? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Hamiltonian circuit problem</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The 0/1 Knapsack problem</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Finding bi-connected components of a graph</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The graph coloring problem</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Finding bi-connected components of a graph</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/561/gate1992-02-vi\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 17,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only: <br>\nFollowing algorithm(s) can be used to sort n in the range \\([1\\ldots n^3]\\) in O(n) time <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1992)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Heap sort</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Quick sort</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Merge sort</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Radix sort</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Radix sort</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/559/gate1992-02-ix\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 18,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (more than one may be correct) and write the corresponding letters only:<br>Kruskal's algorithm for finding a minimum spanning tree of a weighted graph G with n vertices and m edges has the time complexity of: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1991)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O(mn)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(m+n)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(m \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>E.</b> <p>\\(O(m^2)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>O(mn)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/521/gate1991-03-vi\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 19,
          "question": "<p>Choose the correct alternatives (More than one may be correct).<br>The complexity of comparision based sorting algorithms is: <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1990)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta \\left(n^2\\right)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n\\sqrt n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/84830/gate1990-3-v\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 20,
          "question": "<p>Let P be a quicksort program to sort numbers in ascending order. Let \\(t_{1}\\) and \\(t_{2}\\) be the time taken by the program for the inputs \\(\\left[1 \\ 2 \\ 3 \\ 4\\right]\\) and \\(\\left[5 \\ 4 \\ 3 \\ 2 \\ 1\\right]\\), respectively. Which of the following holds? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 1987)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} = t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\gt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\lt t_{2}\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(t_{1}=t_{2}+5 \\log 5\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(t_{1} \\lt t_{2}\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/80366/gate1987-1-xviii\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
